A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the President, Office Files of McGeorge Bundy FA617
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the President, Office Files of McGeorge Bundy
1965-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Bundy, McGeorge
FA617
18.3 Cubic Feet
Scope and Contents
The Office of the President, Office Files of McGeorge Bundy, consist of 32 archives boxes of correspondence, memoranda, drafts of policy statements, meeting dockets, agendas and minutes, rapporteur notes, trip itineraries, briefings and notes, Federal Communications Commission (FCC) filings, press releases, interview transcripts, and photographs.
The records document Bundy’s stewardship of the Foundation from 1966 to 1979. They cover a range of topics and reflect his activities and responsibilities as President of the Foundation from 1966 to 1979. Two key matters faced by the Ford Foundation during Bundy's presidency were economic inflation, which necessitated curtailment in Foundation expenditure, and increasing government scrutiny of foundations with the attendant demands for public accountability.
In 1967, 1971, 1974 and 1975, the decline in the stock market caused the Foundation to implement reduced support for its programs. The drop in investment assets combined with economic inflation compelled the Foundation to review its long term commitments with dependent organizations. Bundy’s records contain significant documentation of this issue. The most severe retrenchment occurred in 1975 when the Board of Trustees instructed Foundation officers to reduce management costs and program budgets by 50 percent. Via task forces and other assessment strategies, Bundy and the officers reviewed grant-making and programmatic decisions in order to re-assess program priorities. The 50 percent reduction in grant funds was accompanied by staff reductions of the same percentage. An Advisory Management Committee was appointed to advise on staff cutbacks..
During Bundy's term, the Ford Foundation's program planning and evaluation activities increased substantially. The files include records with information about the self-studies and program reviews that took place during Bundy's presidency. The 1971 "self-study" group interviewed program staff on: program objectives and evaluations; foundation communications; decision-making; and program personnel roles. Merrimon Cuniggim was hired in 1973 as Program Advisor on Management to examine the following topics: the practice of awarding grants to individuals; grant evaluation; relationships with grantees, with the federal government, and with other foundations; affirmative action in the foundation; and institutional priorities. His findings are covered in the 1975 Summaries of Major Reports and Selected Memoranda (report #002789).
Less well documented in the files is the Board of Trustees' "Mt. Kisco meeting." This meeting culminated in the 1976 Future Program Planning Project (report #003450). In addition to these formal self-studies, the budget files are useful summaries of current and retrospective analyses of program policies.
A trend towards increasing professionalization of its philanthropic activities and documenting and regularizing policies and procedures, marked the Ford Foundation during the Bundy era. Two major factors in this development were the abovementioned economic constraints and government inquiries. The Ford Foundation drew close scrutiny from the House Ways and Means Committee and the Senate Finance Committee. The 1969 Tax Reform Act legislated greater public accountability than foundations had faced previously: a minimum payout of 6 percent of assets, grant "expenditure responsibility," and a 4 percent excise tax on net investment of income. Further, the economic climate forced a recognition that, despite its size, the Foundation did have limited resources. Therefore, program priorities and choices had to be carefully identified.
In the late 1960s and the 1970s, the Ford Foundation increased its grant-making in public policy development. Start-up grants were given to the Council on Legal Education and Professional Responsibility, the Energy Policy Project, and the Police Foundation, in addition to large grants to the Brookings Institution and other public interest organizations. The Ford Foundation established the Committee on Public Policy and Social Responsibility in 1972 to administer grants in this area. This grant-making is covered in Bundy's records.
School decentralization is another issue covered in Bundy’s subject files. In 1967, Mayor John V. Lindsay appointed the Mayor's Advisory Panel on the Decentralization of New York City Schools with Bundy serving as its Chair, to recommend a plan for decentralization and greater community control of the city’s public schools. The files have records of panel meetings, reports and correspondence with other Panel members as well as the Panel staff, some of whom were also Foundation staff (Mitchell Sviridoff, Mario Fantini, Richard Magat). For additional information about decentralization, see the grant files that supported this activity, the files of Richard Magat--Office of Reports and the records of the Mayor’s Advisory Panel (ACC91/3).
The office files include information on the impact of affirmative action on the Foundation's work. Policy development and implementation of internal and external (grantee) affirmative action are covered in the subject files under: Ford Foundation and Women, Co-ordinating Committee on Women's Programs, and External Affirmative Action. Supplemental information on this topic is in the operations and administration files under: Merrimon Cuninggim, Howard Dressner, and Arthur Trottenberg.
Subject files--Television include materials covering the development of a plan for a model communications satellite system that was submitted to the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) in 1966. This plan called for a private, nonprofit satellite that would charge commercial networks for use. Revenues of the satellite were to be used toward funding nonprofit educational television. The development of the Broadcasters' Nonprofit System (BNS) proposal is documented in FCC filings, letters, and memoranda. Key figures in the development of the model communications satellite system proposal include Howard Dressner, Fred Friendly, David Ginsberg, Abraham Katz, and Lee Marks.
Material regarding the social responsibility aspect of investments is contained in the office files. In 1968, the Foundation initiated program-related investments (PRI), a philanthropic mechanism of equity investments and loans to support work relevant to the program areas. In June 1971, the Trustes formally adopted a 'socially responsible' investment policy: "The Foundation's investment policies, and their administration, shall serve the Foundation's scientific, educational, and charitable purposes, for all the public welfare." Correspondence among Bevis Longstreth, David Rosenbloom, Roger Kennedy and McGeorge Bundy provides useful documentation on the Development of the socially responsible investments policy.
Additional topics in the subject files include: rights for the underprivileged; the development of public interest law and policy; the balance of U.S. payments overseas; higher education and government sponsored research; equalizing educational opportunities; the Pay As You Earn (PAYE) program; arms control; and relationships with grantees. In the correspondence files, there is extensive correspondence with the following Foundation staff: David E. Bell, Merrimon Cuninggim, Howard Dressner, Fred Friendly, Harold Howe II, W. McNeil Lowry, Richard Magat, Mitchell Sviridoff, Arthur D. Trottenberg, and F. Champion Ward. There is also substantial correspondence with: Isaiah Berlin, Norman Cousins, John W. Gardner, David Ginsberg, Bevis Longstreth, Michael Mansfield, Lee Marks, Manning Pattillo, Alan Pifer, and Yasushi Sugiyama.
Two areas that receive unexpectedly limited documentation in Bundy’s records are: the Travel and Study Awards given to the former staff of Senator Robert F. Kennedy in 1968 and the Common Fund for Nonprofit Organizations (the college endowment management program). There are only occasional letters and memoranda which make references to these issues. Information is available in other archival holdings on these and other areas not significantly documented in McGeorge Bundy’s office files.
Biographical / Historical
McGeorge Bundy was President of the Ford Foundation from March 1966 until his retirement in May 1979.
Bundy was born March 30, 1919. He received his A.B. degree in 1940 from Yale University. Prior to his tenure with the Ford Foundation, Mr. Bundy held the following positions:
1948-49 Political Analyst, Council on Foreign Relations; 1949-51 Visiting Lecturer, Government, Harvard University; 1951-54 Associate Professor, Government, Harvard University; 1953-61 Dean, School of Arts & Sciences, Harvard University; 1954-61 Professor, Government, Harvard University; 1961-66 Special Assistant to the President for National Security, The White House
After leaving the Foundation in 1979, Bundy became a professor of history at New York University for 10 years In 1990, he joined the Carnegie Corporation of New York.
Bundy's publications include: On Active Service in Peace and War, 1948 (co-authored with Henry L. Stimson); Pattern of Responsibility, 1952 (editor); The Strength of Government, 1968; Danger and Survival: Choices About the Bomb in the First 50 Years, 1988.
McGeorge Bundy died in Boston on September 16, 1996.
Arrangement
The Office of the President, Office Files of McGeorge Bundy are arranged into seven series:
I. OPERATIONS and ADMINISTRATION; II. SUBJECT FILES; III. CORRESPONDENCE and MEMORANDA TO STAFF; IV. TRUSTEE FILES; V. BUDGET FILES; VI. TRIP FILES; VII. PARALLEL FILES (Restricted Access)
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Separated Materials
Budget papers, speeches, and reports by staff and consultants were transferred to their respective collections in the Ford Foundation archives. Transfers are noted on cross-reference sheets in Bundy’s records. Appendices to this register list reports, Budget and Finance papers and speeches that were transferred. Drafts of letters and reports were removed except when no final version was located or when the drafts reflect the evolution of policy, in which case the drafts were retained.
Related Materials
The Ford Foundation’s Annual Reports for the years of Bundy’s presidency--especially the "President's Review" section--will provide the interested researcher with background information about topics that are documented in Bundy's office files. The Ford Foundation archives holds additional sources of information about many subjects covered in the files: grant files, reports, the office files of David Bell (Vice President, International Division, 1966-1981), and the office files of Richard Magat (Director, Office of Reports, 1957-1982).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. This collection was originally accessioned by the Ford Foundation in 2004. The files in this collection were transferred to the Ford Foundation’s archives in three accessions between 1979 and 1982. Series were reconstructed and original filing order was retained.
The collection was transferred to, and officially accessioned, by the Rockefeller Archive Center in 2012.
Existence and Location of Copies
All seven series have been preserved on microfilm.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Inflation (Finance); Government and Public Policy; Economics; Governmental investigations; Government and Public Policy -- Philanthropy Charity & the Nonprofit Sector; Mass Communications; Education; Affirmative action programs; Ford Foundation; Bundy, McGeorge
- Operations and Administration, 1966-1979; bulk; I; 6 Box(es)
  Arrangement
  The series is divided into two subseries: OPERATIONS (programs) and ADMINISTRATION
  It is maintained in the order which it was used in the President's office. The files are arranged hierarchically by program and office. (It is suggested that the researcher use the staff listing in the Annual Reports to facilitate access.)
  Items within each folder are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence, memoranda, drafts of policy statements, and notes.
  Consists of memoranda to Bundy from office, program, and division heads including: David Bell, Howard Dressner, Fred W. Friendly, Harold Howe II, Roger Kennedy, W. McNeil Lowry, Richard Magat, Marshall Robinson, Mitchell Sviridoff, and Arthur Trottenberg, as well as from some program officers. There are some answering memoranda from Bundy. This series is especially strong in program and policy development, administration, retrenchment of Foundation programs, government-foundation relations, program-related investments, and socially responsible investments.
  This series is best used in conjunction with Series II, Subject Files.
  - OPERATIONS, A
    - DIVISION OF EDUCATION AND RESEARCH, 1
      - Howe, Harold II/Vice President (SEE ALSO: INTERNATIONAL DIVISION/Ward), 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
      - Armsey, James W./Program Advisor, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
      - Crossland, Fred E./Program Officer, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Higher Education and Research - Robinson, Marshall A./Officer in Charge, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Higher Education and Research - de Janosi, Peter E./Officer in Charge, 1973 - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Higher Education and Research - Fantini, Mario D. Program Officer, 1966 - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Higher Education and Research - Griffiths, George H./Program Officer, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Higher Education and Research - Schmid, Robert C./Program Officer, 1970 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Higher Education and Research - Payton, Benjamin F./Program Officer, 1971 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Higher Education and Research - Cheit, Earl F./Program Advisor, 1972 - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Public Education - Meade, Edward J. Jr./Officer in Charge, 1966 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
      - Public Education - Bohrson, Ralph G. Program Officer, 1969 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - DIVISION OF HUMANITIES AND THE ARTS, 2
      - Division of Humanities and the Arts, 1966, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Lowry, W. McNeil/Vice President, 1966 - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
      - Letters from Senators re Lowry (SEE ALSO: OFFICE OF THE ARTS/Kennedy), 1973 - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Office of Humanities and the Arts - Richard C. Sheldon/Program Officer, 1970 - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Office of Humanities and the Arts - Thompson, Marcia T./Program Officer, 1973 - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Office of Humanities and the Arts - Lobanov, Oleg/Program Officer, 1974 - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Office of the Arts - Kennedy, Roger G. Vice President (SEE ALSO: DIVISION OF HUMANITIES AND THE ARTS/Sheldon, DIVISION OF FINANCIAL AFFAIRS/Kennedy), 1977 - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - DIVISION OF NATIONAL AFFAIRS, 3
      - Division of National Affairs, 1967 - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Sviridoff, Mitchell/Vice President, 1967 - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
      - Government and Law - Edley, Christopher F./Officer in Charge, 1968 - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Government and Law - Jaffe, Sanford M./Officer in Charge, 1968 - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Government and Law - Grinker, William J./Program Officer, 1971 - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Government and Law - Dodds, R. Harcourt/Program Officer, 1976 - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Resources and the Environment - Harrison, Gordon/Officer in Charge (SEE ALSO: OFFICE OF RESOURCES AND THE ENVIRONMENT/Robinson), 1966 - 1973 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Social Development - Coleman, John/Officer in Charge, 1966 - 1967 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Social Development - Wilkins, Roger W./Officer in Charge, 1966 - 1967 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - OFFICE OF RESOURCES AND THE ENVIRONMENT, 4
      - Robinson, Marshall A./Vice President (SEE ALSO: DIVISION OF NATIONAL AFFAIRS Resources and the Environment/Harrison), 1971 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
    - INTERNATIONAL DIVISION, 5
      - International Division, 1968 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Bell, David E./Vice President, 1966 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 39-41)
      - Sutton, Francis X./Deputy Vice President, 1968 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Hardin, Lowell/Program Officer, 1967 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Ward, F. Champion/Program Advisor, 1966 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 44-46)
      - European and International Affairs - European and International Affairs, 1969 - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - European and International Affairs - Goodwin, Craufurd D./Officer in Charge, 1971 - 1973 (Box 4, Folder 48-49)
      - European and International Affairs - Bader, William B./Program Officer, 1969 - 1974 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - European and International Affairs - Silj, Alessandro/Program Officer, 1971 - 1973 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - European and International Affairs - Schoettle, Enid C.B./Program Officer, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - European and International Affairs - Heaps, David/Program Officer, 1973 - 1976 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Population - Harkavy, Oscar/Officer in Charge, 1968 - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Asia and the Pacific - Asia, 1966 - 1978 (Box 5, Folder 55)
      - Asia and the Pacific - Staples, Eugene S./Head, 1967 - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 56-58)
      - Asia and the Pacific - Bresnan, John/Head, 1973 - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      - Asia and the Pacific - Miller, Frank J./Deputy, 1970 - 1975 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      - India and Nepal - India, 1966-1974 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - India and Nepal - Wilhelm, Harry E./Representative, 1973 - 1975 (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Pakistan, 1970 - 1971 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - Bangladesh, 1972 - 1975 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Southeast Asia - Vietnam, 1973 - 1975 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - Middle East and Africa, 1967 - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Middle East and Africa - Fredericks, Wayne/Head, 1966 - 1973 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - Middle East and Africa - Edwards, Robert H./Head, 1973 - 1977 (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - Eastern and Southern Africa - Southern Africa, 1972 - 1973 (Box 6, Folder 69)
      - Latin America and Caribbean, 1966 - 1976 (Box 6, Folder 70)
      - Latin America and Caribbean - Carmichael, William D./Head, 1971 - 1977 (Box 6, Folder 71)
      - Latin America and Caribbean - Nagel, John S./Deputy and Program Officer, 1970 - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 72)
      - Peru, Bolivia and Ecuador - Lowenthal, Abraham F./Asst. Representative, 1966 - 1972 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - OFFICE OF PUBLIC BROADCASTING, 6
      - Davis, David M./Officer in Charge (SEE ALSO: OFFICE OF THE PRESIDENT/Friendly), 1969 - 1978 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - OFFICE OF COMMUNICATIONS, 7
      Related Materials
      SEE ALSO: OFFICE OF PUBLIC BROADCASTING
    - OFFICE OF THE PRESIDENT, 8
      - Stone, Shep/Advisor on Special International Activities, 1966 - 1967 (Box 7, Folder 75)
      - Bowles, Frank/Advisor on International Education, 1966 - 1968 (Box 7, Folder 76)
      - Borgmann, Carl W./Advisor on Science and Technology, 1966 - 1969 (Box 7, Folder 77)
      - Friendly, Fred W./Advisor on Television, 1966 - 1979 (Box 7, Folder 78)
      - Bohen, Frederick/Assistant to the President, 1968 - 1972 (Box 7, Folder 79)
      - Strasburg, Paul./Assistant to the President, 1972 - 1973 (Box 7, Folder 80)
      - Smith, Theodore M./Assistant to the President, 1974 - 1975 (Box 7, Folder 81)
      - Cuninggim, Merrimon/Program Advisor, 1972 - 1976 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - ADMINISTRATION, B
    - DIVISION OF ADMINISTRATION, 1
      - Trottenberg, Arthur D./Vice President, 1968 - 1979 (Box 7, Folder 83-85)
      - Program-Related Investments, 1972 - 1975 (Box 7, Folder 86)
      - Program-Related Investments - Kelly, Eamon M./Officer in Charge, 1975 - 1979 (Box 8, Folder 87)
      - Personnel Services - Gormbley, William P./Officer in Charge, 1975 - 1979 (Box 8, Folder 88)
      - Personnel Services - Osborn, Dorothy J./Administrative Officer, 1971 - 1978 (Box 8, Folder 89)
      - Logistical Services - Mayer, Robert A./Officer in Charge, 1968 - 1971 (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - OFFICE OF THE SECRETARY AND GENERAL COUNSEL, 2
      - Dressner, Howard R./Secretary and General Counsel, 1967 - 1979 (Box 8, Folder 91-96)
      - Hertz, Willard J./Asst. Secretary, 1973 - 1978 (Box 8, Folder 97)
      - McLean, Sheila A./Assoc. General Counsel, 1972, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - DIVISION OF FINANCIAL AFFAIRS, 3
      - Office of Financial Affairs - Kennedy, Roger G./Vice President (SEE ALSO: OFFICE OF THE ARTS/Kennedy), 1972 - 1974 (Box 9, Folder 99-104)
      - Office of the Treasurer - Lenagh, Thomas H./Treasurer, 1968 - 1978 (Box 9, Folder 105)
      - Office of the Treasurer - Clemente, Lilia C./Asst. Treasurer, 1968 - 1978 (Box 9, Folder 106)
      - Hagler, Jon L./Vice President and Treasurer (SEE ALSO: OFFICE OF FINANCIAL AFFAIRS/Office of the Treasurer), 1977 - 1978 (Box 9, Folder 107)
    - OFFICE OF REPORTS, 4
      - Richard Magat/Director and Editor, 1967 - 1979 (Box 9, Folder 108-110)
      - Boggs, Nancy H./Administrative Officer, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 111)
- Subject Files, 1969-1976; bulk; II; 13 Box(es)
  It is arranged alphabetically by topic or name.
  Cross-references are included in the folder listing to facilitate access among related topics.
  Series II consists of correspondence, memoranda, agendas, minutes, rapporteur notes, reports, FCC filings, and press releases.
  Contains the topical subject files. Series II documents many of the activities and issues in which the Ford Foundation was involved: affirmative action within and outside of the Foundation; retrenchment and dependent organizations; Foundation self-evaluation and future program planning; public interest law; public television and the proposed Broadcaster's Nonprofit Satellite; foundation-government relations including public policy development, government and higher education research, and the Tax Reform Act of 1969; and decentralization of New York City schools.
  - Administrative Plans, Post Atwater, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Advisory Management Committee, 1974 - 1976 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Affirmative Action - Women and Minorities (SEE ALSO: Ford Foundation and Women, Co-ordinating Committee on Women's Programs, External Affirmative Action), 1972 - 1978 (Box 10, Folder 114-115)
  - Alaska Native Foundation Letter, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - American Value Meeting, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 117)
    SEE ALSO: Future of American Society
  - Annual Report, 1976 - 1979 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - Arms Control, 1972 - 1979 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Atlantic Institute, 1972 - 1973 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Balance of Payments, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Bellagio, 1973, 1975 - 1976 (Box 10, Folder 122-124)
  - Berelson, Bernard, n.d., 1974 (Box 10, Folder 125)
  - Berlin, Isaiah (Box 11, Folder -)
    SEE: Wolfson College
  - Brookings - British Brookings, 1977 - 1978 (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Brookings - International Brookings, 1976 - 1977 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - Budget, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 128)
    SEE ALSO: Series V, Budget